[Music]
This is a three. It's sloppily written
and rendered at an extremely low
resolution of 28x 28 pixels. But your
brain has no trouble recognizing it as a
three. And I want you to take a moment
to appreciate how crazy it is that
brains can do this so effortlessly. I
mean this, this, and this are also
recognizable as threes. Even though the
specific values of each pixel is very
different from one image to the next,
the particular light sensitive cells in
your eye that are firing when you see
this three are very different from the
ones firing when you see this three. But
something in that crazy smart visual
cortex of yours resolves these as
representing the same idea while at the
same time recognizing other images as
their own distinct ideas. But if I told
you, hey, sit down and write for me a
program that takes in a grid of 28x 28
pixels like this and outputs a single
number between 0 and 10, telling you
what it thinks the digit is. While the
task goes from comically trivial to
dauntingly difficult, unless you've been
living under a rock, I think I hardly
need to motivate the relevance and
importance of machine learning and
neural networks to the present and to
the future. But what I want to do here
is show you what a neural network
actually is, assuming no background, and
to help visualize what it's doing, not
as a buzzword, but as a piece of math.
My hope is just that you come away
feeling like the structure itself is
motivated and to feel like you know what
it means when you read or you hear about
a neural network, quote unquote,
learning. This video is just going to be
devoted to the structure component of
that. And the following one is going to
tackle learning. What we're going to do
is put together a neural network that
can learn to recognize handwritten
digits.
This is a somewhat classic example for
introducing the topic. And I'm happy to
stick with the status quo here because
at the end of the two videos, I want to
point you to a couple good resources
where you can learn more and where you
can download the code that does this and
play with it on your own computer.
There are many many variants of neural
networks and in recent years there's
been sort of a boom in research towards
these variants. But in these two
introductory videos, you and I are just
going to look at the simplest plain
vanilla form with no added frills. This
is kind of a necessary prerequisite for
understanding any of the more powerful
modern variants. And trust me, it still
has plenty of complexity for us to wrap
our minds around. But even in this
simplest form, it can learn to recognize
handwritten digits, which is a pretty
cool thing for a computer to be able to
do. And at the same time, you'll see how
it does fall short of a couple hopes
that we might have for it.
As the name suggests, neural networks
are inspired by the brain. But let's
break that down. What are the neurons,
and in what sense are they linked
together? Right now, when I say neuron,
all I want you to think about is a thing
that holds a number. specifically a
number between zero and one. It's really
not more than that.
For example, the network starts with a
bunch of neurons corresponding to each
of the 28 * 28 pixels of the input
image, which is 784 neurons in total.
Each one of these holds a number that
represents the grayscale value of the
corresponding pixel, ranging from zero
for black pixels up to one for white
pixels. This number inside the neuron is
called its activation. And the image you
might have in mind here is that each
neuron is lit up when its activation is
a high number.
So all of these 784 neurons make up the
first layer of our network.
Now jumping over to the last layer. This
has 10 neurons each representing one of
the digits. The activation in these
neurons, again, some number that's
between 0 and 1, represents how much the
system thinks that a given image
corresponds with a given digit. There's
also a couple layers in between called
the hidden layers, which for the time
being should just be a giant question
mark for how on earth this process of
recognizing digits is going to be
handled. In this network, I chose two
hidden layers, each one with 16 neurons.
And admittedly, that's kind of an
arbitrary choice to be honest. I chose
two layers based on how I want to
motivate the structure in just a moment.
And 16, well, that was just a nice
number to fit on the screen. In
practice, there is a lot of room for
experiment with a specific structure
here. The way the network operates,
activations in one layer determine the
activations of the next layer. And of
course, the heart of the network as an
information processing mechanism comes
down to exactly how those activations
from one layer bring about activations
in the next layer. It's meant to be
loosely analogous to how in biological
networks of neurons, some groups of
neurons firing cause certain others to
fire. Now, the network I'm showing here
has already been trained to recognize
digits. And let me show you what I mean
by that. It means if you feed in an
image lighting up all 784 neurons of the
input layer according to the brightness
of each pixel in the image, that pattern
of activations causes some very specific
pattern in the next layer, which causes
some pattern in the one after it, which
finally gives some pattern in the output
layer. And the brightest neuron of that
output layer is the network's choice, so
to speak, for what digit this image
represents.
And before jumping into the math for how
one layer influences the next or how
training works, let's just talk about
why it's even reasonable to expect a
layered structure like this to behave
intelligently. What are we expecting
here? What is the best hope for what
those middle layers might be doing?
Well, when you or I recognize digits, we
piece together various components. A 9
has a loop up top and a line on the
right. An eight also has a loop up top,
but it's paired with another loop down
low. A four basically breaks down into
three specific lines and things like
that. Now, in a perfect world, we might
hope that each neuron in the second to
last layer corresponds with one of these
subcomponents. That anytime you feed in
an image with, say, a loop up top, like
a 9 or an 8, there's some specific
neuron whose activation is going to be
close to one. And I don't mean this
specific loop of pixels. The hope would
be that any generally loopy pattern
towards the top sets off this neuron.
That way, going from the third layer to
the last one just requires learning
which combination of subcomponents
corresponds to which digits. Of course,
that just kicks the problem down the
road because how would you recognize
these subcomponents or even learn what
the right subcomponents should be? And I
still haven't even talked about how one
layer influences the next. But run with
me on this one for a moment. Recognizing
a loop can also break down into subpros.
One reasonable way to do this would be
to first recognize the various little
edges that make it up. Similarly, a long
line like the kind you might see in the
digits 1 or four or seven. Well, that's
really just a long edge. Or maybe you
think of it as a certain pattern of
several smaller edges. So maybe our hope
is that each neuron in the second layer
of the network corresponds with the
various relevant little edges. Maybe
when an image like this one comes in, it
lights up all of the neurons associated
with around 8 to 10 specific little
edges, which in turn lights up the
neurons associated with the upper loop
and a long vertical line, and those
light up the neuron associated with a
nine. Whether or not this is what our
final network actually does is another
question, one that I'll come back to
once we see how to train the network.
But this is a hope that we might have a
sort of goal with the layered structure
like this. Moreover, you can imagine how
being able to detect edges and patterns
like this would be really useful for
other image recognition tasks. And even
beyond image recognition, there are all
sorts of intelligent things you might
want to do that break down into layers
of abstraction. Parsing speech, for
example, involves taking raw audio and
picking out distinct sounds which
combine to make certain syllables, which
combine to form words, which combine to
make up phrases and more abstract
thoughts, etc. But getting back to how
any of this actually works, picture
yourself right now designing how exactly
the activations in one layer might
determine the activations in the next.
The goal is to have some mechanism that
could conceivably combine pixels into
edges or edges into patterns or patterns
into digits. And to zoom in on one very
specific example, let's say the hope is
for one particular neuron in the second
layer to pick up on whether or not the
image has an edge in this region here.
The question at hand is what parameters
should the network have? What dials and
knobs should you be able to tweak so
that it's expressive enough to
potentially capture this pattern or any
other pixel pattern or the pattern that
several edges can make a loop and other
such things. Well, what we'll do is
assign a weight to each one of the
connections between our neuron and the
neurons from the first layer. These
weights are just numbers. Then take all
of those activations from the first
layer and compute their weighted sum
according to these weights.
I find it helpful to think of these
weights as being organized into a little
grid of their own. And I'm going to use
green pixels to indicate positive
weights and red pixels to indicate
negative weights where the brightness of
that pixel is some loose depiction of
the weights value. Now, if we made the
weights associated with almost all of
the pixels zero, except for some
positive weights in this region that we
care about, then taking the weighted sum
of all the pixel values really just
amounts to adding up the values of the
pixel just in the region that we care
about.
And if you really wanted to pick up on
whether there's an edge here, what you
might do is have some negative weights
associated with the surrounding pixels.
Then the sum is largest when those
middle pixels are bright but the
surrounding pixels are darker.
When you compute a weighted sum like
this, you might come out with any
number. But for this network, what we
want is for activations to be some value
between 0 and 1. So a common thing to do
is to pump this weighted sum into some
function that squishes the real number
line into the range between 0 and 1. And
a common function that does this is
called the sigmoid function, also known
as a logistic curve. Basically, very
negative inputs end up close to zero,
very positive inputs end up close to
one, and it just steadily increases
around the input zero.
So, the activation of the neuron here is
basically a measure of how positive the
relevant weighted sum is.
But maybe it's not that you want the
neuron to light up when the weighted sum
is bigger than zero. Maybe you only want
it to be active when the sum is bigger
than say 10. That is you want some bias
for it to be inactive.
What we'll do then is just add in some
other number like -10 to this weighted
sum before plugging it through the
sigmoid squishification function. That
additional number is called the bias. So
the weights tell you what pixel pattern
this neuron in the second layer is
picking up on and the bias tells you how
high the weighted sum needs to be before
the neuron starts getting meaningfully
active. And that is just one neuron.
Every other neuron in this layer is
going to be connected to all 784 pixel
neurons from the first layer. And each
one of those 784 connections has its own
weight associated with it. Also, each
one has some bias, some other number
that you add on to the weighted sum
before squishing it with the sigmoid.
And that's a lot to think about. With
this hidden layer of 16 neurons, that's
a total of 784*
16 weights along with 16 biases. And all
of that is just the connections from the
first layer to the second. The
connections between the other layers
also have a bunch of weights and biases
associated with them. All said and done,
this network has almost exactly 13,000
total weights and biases. 13,000 knobs
and dials that can be tweaked and turned
to make this network behave in different
ways. So when we talk about learning,
what that's referring to is getting the
computer to find a valid setting for all
of these many, many numbers so that
it'll actually solve the problem at
hand.
One thought experiment that is at once
fun and kind of horrifying is to imagine
sitting down and setting all of these
weights and biases by hand, purposefully
tweaking the numbers so that the second
layer picks up on edges, the third layer
picks up on patterns, etc. I personally
find this satisfying rather than just
treating the network as a total black
box. Because when the network doesn't
perform the way you anticipate, if
you've built up a little bit of a
relationship with what those weights and
biases actually mean, you have a
starting place for experimenting with
how to change the structure to improve
or when the network does work, but not
for the reasons you might expect.
Digging into what the weights and biases
are doing is a good way to challenge
your assumptions and really expose the
full space of possible solutions. By the
way, the actual function here is a
little cumbersome to write down, don't
you think?
So, let me show you a more notationally
compact way that these connections are
represented. This is how you'd see it if
you choose to read up more about neural
networks. Organize all of the
activations from one layer into a column
as a vector.
Then, organize all of the weights as a
matrix where each row of that matrix
corresponds to the connections between
one layer and a particular neuron in the
next layer. What that means is that
taking the weighted sum of the
activations in the first layer according
to these weights corresponds to one of
the terms in the matrix vector product
of everything we have on the left here.
By the way, so much of machine learning
just comes down to having a good grasp
of linear algebra. So for any of you who
want a nice visual understanding for
matrices and what matrix vector
multiplication means, take a look at the
series I did on linear algebra,
especially chapter 3. Back to our
expression, instead of talking about
adding the bias to each one of these
values independently, we represent it by
organizing all those biases into a
vector and adding the entire vector to
the previous matrix vector product. Then
as a final step, I'll wrap a sigmoid
around the outside here. And what that's
supposed to represent is that you're
going to apply the sigmoid function to
each specific component of the resulting
vector inside.
So once you write down this weight
matrix and these vectors as their own
symbols, you can communicate the full
transition of activations from one layer
to the next in an extremely tight and
neat little expression. And this makes
the relevant code both a lot simpler and
a lot faster since many libraries
optimize the heck out of matrix
multiplication.
Remember
how earlier I said these neurons are
simply things that hold numbers? Well,
of course, the specific numbers that
they hold depends on the image you feed
in.
So, it's actually more accurate to think
of each neuron as a function. One that
takes in the outputs of all the neurons
in the previous layer and spits out a
number between 0 and 1. Really, the
entire network is just a function. one
that takes in 784 numbers as an input
and spits out 10 numbers as an output.
It's an absurdly complicated function,
one that involves 13,000 parameters in
the forms of these weights and biases
that pick up on certain patterns and
which involves iterating many matrix
vector products and the sigmoid
squishification function. But it's just
a function nonetheless. And in a way,
it's kind of reassuring that it looks
complicated. I mean, if it were any
simpler, what hope would we have that it
could take on the challenge of
recognizing digits? And how does it take
on that challenge? How does this network
learn the appropriate weights and biases
just by looking at data? Well, that's
what I'll show in the next video. And
I'll also dig a little more into what
this particular network we're seeing is
really doing.
Now is the point I suppose I should say
subscribe to stay notified about when
that video or any new videos come out.
But realistically, most of you don't
actually receive notifications from
YouTube, do you? Maybe more honestly, I
should say subscribe so that the neural
networks that underly YouTube's
recommendation algorithm are primed to
believe that you want to see content
from this channel get recommended to
you. Anyway, stay posted for more. Thank
you very much to everyone supporting
these videos on Patreon. I've been a
little slow to progress in the
probability series this summer, but I'm
jumping back into it after this project.
So, patrons, you can look out for
updates there.
To close things off here, I have with me
Leysa Lee, who did her PhD work on the
theoretical side of deep learning and
who currently works at a venture capital
firm called Amplify Partners, who kindly
provided some of the funding for this
video. So, Leysa, one thing I think we
should quickly bring up is this sigmoid
function. As I understand it, early
networks used this to squish the
relevant weighted sum into that interval
between 0 and one. You know, kind of
motivated by this biological analogy of
neurons either being inactive or active.
Exactly. But relatively few modern
networks actually use sigmoid anymore.
That's kind of old school, right?
Yeah. Or rather, relu seems to be much
easier to train.
And relu relu stands for rectified
linear unit.
Yes. It's this kind of function where
you're just taking a max of zero and a
where a is given by what you were
explaining in the video. And what this
was sort of motivated from, I think, was
a partially by a biological analogy with
how neurons would either be activated or
not. And so if it passes a certain
threshold, it would be the identity
function, but if it did not, then it
would just not be activated. So be zero.
So it's kind of a simplification. Using
sigmoids didn't help training or it was
very difficult to train at at some
point. and people just tried ReLU and it
happened to work very well for these
incredibly um deep uh neural networks.
All right, thank you Alicia.
[Music]